Institute of Fisheries Analysis fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Institute of Fisheries Analysis fonds
1960 - 1998
F-240
1.75 m of textual records 1 architectural drawing
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Institute of Fisheries Analysis
The Institute of Fisheries Analysis (IFA) was founded in 1980 by Dr. Parzival Copes, an economist and charter faculty member at Simon Fraser University (SFU), with the support of faculty members who held a common interest in fisheries research. The IFA was established to promote interdisciplinary study and research on fisheries questions among SFU faculty, staff, and students. Topical areas of interest included, but were not limited to, the basic biology, ecology, and population dynamics of exploitable fish stocks; the bio-economic and socio-political framework of fisheries regulation and management; the socio-economic well-being of fishing communities; industrial and commercial developments related to fisheries; and the political economy of the fishing industry. In 2001, the IFA was dissolved and succeeded by the Centre for Coastal Studies.
In conjunction with its objective to promote interdisciplinary fisheries studies and research, the IFA sponsored interdisciplinary research seminars in fisheries and encouraged research cooperation among persons from relevant disciplines. The Institute also assisted in securing and administering resources for fisheries research conducted at the University. Although the IFA did not have a formal teaching role, it did encourage and support teaching programs in fisheries analysis by providing background research as well as guidance and academic supervision to students admitted to master’s or doctoral programs in fisheries management under Special Arrangements (i.e., graduate studies programs outside or between existing graduate programs, administered by the Dean of Graduate Studies).
The Institute, through using the services and expertise of its members, undertook research contracts external to the University. In order to disseminate research carried out by its members, the IFA published a Discussion Paper Series, which later evolved into the series titled Fisheries Research Papers.
When the IFA was first founded, the directorship and administration were combined with that of the Centre for Canadian Studies (CNS) as Copes was the director of CNS at the time. CNS received resources from the Office of the Vice-President, Research and Information Systems to support all of the IFA’s administrative needs. Around 1988, CNS and the IFA were separated, and the IFA was allocated its own physical space where a library and fisheries-related bibliography were developed and maintained for the use of researchers. This separation resulted in a lack of support staff and regular budget for the IFA.
In 1989, the IFA entered into a Collaborative Research and Training Agreement with Simon Fraser University and the Asian Fisheries and Social Science Research Network (AFSSRN), which was sponsored by the International Development Research Centre (IDRC). The purpose of this agreement was to provide opportunities at SFU for members of the AFSSRN to obtain master’s and doctoral qualifications in fisheries economics under the supervision of SFU faculty members from the IFA. This was a major source of IFA funding, along with a small amount of funding provided through the Faculty of Arts, and various research grants obtained by individual members of the Institute for various projects.
The administration of the IFA consisted of a Governing Committee—initially comprised of the Deans of Arts, Graduate Studies, Interdisciplinary Studies, and Science—a Director, and an Associate Director. The Director and Associate Director were appointed by the Governing Committee in consultation with the regular members of the Institute (i.e., persons holding faculty or research appointments at SFU) and the associate members of the Institute (i.e., students of the University who were directly involved in the work of the Institute). Nominations made to the Governing Committee for the Director and Associate Director were made by majority vote of the members. Applications for membership to the Institution were made to the Director and approved by majority vote of the Institute’s regular members. The Director reported directly to the Dean of Arts.
The Institute was dissolved in 2001, and its successor, the Centre for Coastal Studies, expanded the IFA’s original mandate, taking a broader ecosystem approach to coastal resource research and management.
published
Full
Published
Title is based on the name of the fonds creator.
The fonds consists of records made and received by the Institute of Fisheries Analysis in the course of administering its day-to-day operations. Activities and topics documented include the establishment, organization, and operation of the Institute (including its physical space); budget and funding; projects, programs, and agreements; IFA publications and publicity; and student, staff, and IFA member relations. Records in the fonds include correspondence, minutes, contracts, internal directories, reports, discussion papers, subject files (relating to fisheries research), press clippings, and IFA brochures.
Note that the records of the Institute of Fisheries Analysis contain university records from the Centre for Canadian Studies and the Department of Economics and Commerce. This anomaly likely occurred because of Parzival Copes’s involvement as director and instructor within each of these bodies. The records he used would have been maintained together in whichever office he occupied. For further information on these records see the descriptions and notes for Series F-240-5: Centre for Canadian Studies records and Series F-240-6: Department of Economics and Commerce records.
When the records were originally donated to the Archives, they were combined in a disorderly fashion with the personal records of Parzival Copes. In order to provide access to the materials, in 2010, the archivist segregated those records comprising the Institute of Fisheries Analysis (IFA) fonds from those comprising Copes's fonds. Series were then assigned to the IFA records, based on the functions and activities of the body. Where necessary, loose materials were placed into files, and assigned titles based on the content of the folder. Those titles, which were supplied by the archivist, are enclosed in square brackets.
As the records of the Department of Economics and Commerce (DEC) and the Centre for Canadian Studies (CnS) were so intermingled with the records of the IFA, the archivist decided to leave all records together in the Institute of Fisheries Analysis fonds. During arrangement and description the files and loose items, which were easily attributed to the DEC and CnS, were separated from the other items and files, and assigned to separate series within the fonds—series F-240-5: Centre for Canadian Studies records, and series F-240-6: Department of Economics records.
Heaps, Terry; Copes, Parzival; Brown, Robert C.; Architectural drawings; Textual records; Education; Business and commerce; Environment
Parzival Copes donated the records to the Simon Fraser University Archives in one accession in 2008.
As of 2010 all accessions have been processed. Further accruals to the fonds as a whole are expected.
Note that a further accession of records from Parzival Copes is expected, and that this accession may contain more materials relevant to the Institute of Fisheries Analysis, the Centre for Canadian Studies, and the Department of Economics. If this is the case, there will be more accruals arranged into the appropriate series.
The records of the Institute Fisheries Analysis (IFA) were in the custody of the Institute until 2001, when its successor, the Centre for Coastal Studies, took over the IFA's physical space. At that time, all of the IFA's records were boxed together with Parzival Copes's personal records and shipped to his home in West Vancouver. The records were stored in his garage until their subsequent donation to the Simon Fraser University Archives in 2008.
For other material relating to the Institute or Fisheries Analysis fonds, see the Parzival Copes fonds finding aid (F-139).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the reference archivist for more details.
Copyright subsists in all or some of the records. Generally, the university is the copyright owner only for works that its employees and service providers authored. Please consult the reference archivist for details about the use of copyrighted materials.
Note that both of these qualifications (restrictions and copyright) apply to files across all series in the fonds. Series descriptions include a note on restrictions only where more specific information is applicable.
Complete file lists are available for all series and sub-series.
- General administrative and subject files, 1980 - 1998; F-240-1; 7 cm of textual records 1 architectual drawing
  published
  Series includes records related to the general administration and organization of the Institute of Fisheries Analysis. Activities and topics documented include research and academic activities; Institute building needs and development; funding and project initiatives—with such organizations as the International Development Research Centre, the Centre for Asia-Pacific Initiatives, and the Canadian International Development Agency; and program operation. Predominant document types include Institute minutes, correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, and one architectural drawing.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged chronologically.
  Canadian International Development Agency; New Building Committee; Centre for Asia-Pacific Initiatives; International Development Research Centre
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  - [IFA minutes], [198-]; F-240-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Research - general, [198-]; F-240-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [IFA general information], [198-] - [199-]; F-240-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - IFA some academic activities at SFU related to fisheries, [198-] - 1994; F-240-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - International Development Research Centre - Papua New Guinea University of Technology, 1981 - 1983; F-240-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
    Creator's original file classification code: PNG.
  - Centre for Asia-Pacific Initiatives, 1988; F-240-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [Canadian International Development Agencies - Thai Delegation], 1989; F-240-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - New Building Committee, vol. 1, 1989 - 1994; F-240-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - New Building Committee [architectual drawing - level 2000 NE furniture plan (F-02A)], vol. 2, 1989 - 1994; F-240-1-0-0-9
  - IFA space needs, 1992 - 1993; F-240-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [Terry Heaps - work to do], 1997 - 1998; F-240-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
- Correspondence, 1977 - 1996; F-240-2; 35 cm of textual records
  Series consists of the incoming and outgoing correspondence of the Institute of Fisheries Analysis, including the director's correspondence on matters relating to Institutional projects and programs, and correspondence with such organizations as the International Centre for Ocean Development (ICOD) and the International Development Research Centre (IDRC). Topical areas covered include research; IFA discussion papers; funding; international relationships; and student inquiries and applications. Records consist of correspondence, memoranda, and reports.
  International Development Research Centre; International Centre for Ocean Development
  - [Director's correspondence], vol. 1, 1977 - 1994; F-240-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [Director's correspondence], vol. 2, 1977 - 1994; F-240-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [Task notes - completed], [198-]; F-240-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [Task notes - new], [198-]; F-240-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - Abgrall, Jean Francois, 1980 - 1981; F-240-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - Enquiries re Institute, vol. 1, 1980 - 1985; F-240-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - Enquiries re Institute, vol. 2, 1980 - 1985; F-240-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 240-1)
  - [IFA memoranda], [198-] - [199-]; F-240-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - International Development Research Centre - Ottawa correspondence, [198-] - [199-]; F-240-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Mills, D.H., 1981; F-240-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Tuomi, A.L.W., 1981; F-240-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Development cooperation with Papua New Guinea Department of Primary Industry, 1981; F-240-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Institutional cooperation with Papua New Guinea University of Technology, 1981 - 1982; F-240-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - [Canadian University Service Overseas] CUSO, 1981 - 1982; F-240-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Stollery, Ken, 1981 - 1982; F-240-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Applications - enquiries graduate studies, 1981 - 1985; F-240-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [A], vol. 1, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [B], vol. 2, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [C], vol. 3, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [D], vol. 4, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [F], vol. 5, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [G], vol. 6, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [H], vol. 7, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [K], vol. 8, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [M], vol. 9, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [N], vol. 10, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [O], vol. 11, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [P], vol. 12, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [R], vol. 13, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [S], vol. 14, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [T], vol. 15, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [W], vol. 16, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - IFA: Requests for discussion papers - papers mailed [Y], vol. 17, 1981 - 1988; F-240-2-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Oliver, John (James Cook University), 1982; F-240-2-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Perrault, Roy J., 1982; F-240-2-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Canadian research, 1982 - 1983; F-240-2-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Graduate student information - scholarships/fellowships, 1982 - 1985; F-240-2-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - [International Center for Ocean Development - correspondence], vol. 1, 1982 - 1986; F-240-2-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - [International Center for Ocean Development - Correspondence], vol. 2, 1982 - 1986; F-240-2-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 240-2)
  - Essay competition - Department of Fisheries and Oceans, 1982 - 1992; F-240-2-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Marine and freshwater scientists in Canada (directory of), 1983; F-240-2-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Jorgensen, Murray A., 1983; F-240-2-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Stearns, Mary Lee, 1983; F-240-2-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - CIRAST Centre d’Intervention et de Recherché pour l’Amélioration des Situations de Travail - Rimouski, 1983 - 1984; F-240-2-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Enquiries re Institute: A-G], vol. 1, 1983 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Enquiries re Institute: A-G], vol. 2, 1983 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Enquiries re Institute: H-Q], vol. 3, 1983 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Enquiries re Institute: H-Q], vol. 4, 1983 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Enquiries re Institute: R-Z], vol. 5, 1983 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-49 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Enquiries re Institute: R-Z], vol. 6, 1983 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-50 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Netboy, Anthony, 1985; F-240-2-0-0-51 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - [Applications - enquiries graduate studies], 1986 - 1987; F-240-2-0-0-52 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Institute for Aquaculture Research, 1988; F-240-2-0-0-53 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Centre for Canadian Studies, 1988; F-240-2-0-0-54 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Correspondence - external, 1988 - 1992; F-240-2-0-0-55 (Archival box - standard 240-3)
  - Canadian Bureau for International Education, 1991; F-240-2-0-0-56 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Canadian Centre for Fisheries Innovation, 1991; F-240-2-0-0-57 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Second Pakistan aquaculture development project, Punjab, 1991; F-240-2-0-0-58 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Prince of Songkla University Hat Yai, Thailand, 1991 - 1992; F-240-2-0-0-59 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - [Correspondence - general], 1991 - 1993; F-240-2-0-0-60 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Environmental research at SFU, 1993; F-240-2-0-0-61 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - SFU Library resources (R. Schwindt), 1993 - 1994; F-240-2-0-0-62 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Chronological file, 1994 - 1996; F-240-2-0-0-63 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
- Printed material and reports, 1976 - 1992; F-240-3; 5 cm of textual records
  Series consists of publications produced by the Institute of Fisheries Analysis relating to its organization, programs, and research. Document types include newsletters, brochures, and research papers.
  - Fisheries Economics Newsletter, vol. 1, 1976 - 1987; F-240-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Fisheries Economics Newsletter, vol. 2, 1976 - 1987; F-240-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - [IFA notes], [198-]; F-240-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - [Documentation of keyword search systems for the Bibliography of Fisheries Analysis with Emphasis on Economics], [198-]; F-240-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - [IFA brochure], [198-?]; F-240-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - [IFA Discussion Paper Series], vol. 1, 1981 - 1987; F-240-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - [IFA Discussion Paper Series], vol. 2, 1981 - 1987; F-240-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Centre for Fisheries and Aquaculture, 1991 - 1992; F-240-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
- Projects, programs, and agreements, 1980 - 1997; F-240-4; 7 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records made and received by the Institute of Fisheries Analysis (IFA) relating to its academic projects, programs, contractual agreements, and research. Topics and activities include the development of a partnership between IFA and the Asian Fisheries and Social Science Research Network; internal and external funding—including funding from the International Development Research Centre; fisheries workshops; and graduate programming. Documents include correspondence, proposals, reports, budget materials, and IFA informational booklets.
  International Development Research Centre; Asian Fisheries and Social Science Research Network
  - [Report: Herring Management Strategy for the Maritimes Region], [198-]; F-240-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Fisheries and Oceans Maritime region, [198-]; F-240-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
    Creator's original file classification code: 710-273-Centre 4803.
  - Alternative vessel fishing licensing combinations, [198-]; F-240-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
    Creator's original file classification code: 710-244-1251.
  - Graduate studies in fisheries management at SFU (master and copies), [198-?]; F-240-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Asian Fisheries and Social Science Research Network/Institute of Fisheries Analysis Cooperative Research Proposal [History of Negotiation], vol. 1, [198-] - [ca 1992]; F-240-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 240-4)
  - Asian Fisheries and Social Science Research Network/Institute of Fisheries Analysis Cooperative Research Proposal [History of Negotiation], vol. 2, [198-] - [ca 1992]; F-240-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
  - Fisheries Management - Graduate Program, [1982?] - [ca 1994]; F-240-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
  - Kasetsart - IFA proposal for Canadian International Development Agencies, 1987; F-240-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
  - Research Fund [International Development Research Centre], 1988 - 1989; F-240-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
    Creator's original file classification code: 1328 IDRC.
  - [Asian Fisheries and Social Science Research Network/Institute of Fisheries Analysis cooperative research proposal], 1989; F-240-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
  - Fisheries Economics Group, [199-]; F-240-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
  - [Speaking for the Salmon workshop], 1997; F-240-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 240-5)
- Centre for Canadian Studies records, 1969 - 1991; F-240-5; 29 cm of textual records; Centre for Canadian Studies
  The Canadian Studies program developed from a series of informal meetings among a group of interested faculty members in late 1969 and early 1970. Subsequently representatives from eight departments and the library drafted a proposal for a Canadian Studies program within the Division of General Studies (later the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies). Course offerings began in the fall of 1971. The program was intended to provide a corrective for the lack of Canadian content being offered in the University and to provide a focus for interdisciplinary study.